<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Creating a Manuscript Description</title>
        <author>TEI @ Oxford</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>August 2016</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Lou Burnard Consulting</publisher>
        <availability>
          <p>Freely available for use and derivative works under a Creative Commons Attribution
            license.</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Various previous talks, TEI Guidelines, etc.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2016-08-09"> First draft </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <!-- Learning Outcomes -->
     <!-- <div>
        <head>Learning Outcomes</head>
        <p>During this exercise you will learn : <list type="bulleted">
            <item>how to create a basic manuscript description </item>
            <item>how the various components of a TEI manuscript description are organized</item>
            <item>how to create a detailed manuscript description</item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
-->


      <div>
        <head>A minimal <gi>msDesc</gi></head>
        <p>A manuscript description, as the name suggests, describes a manuscript. The description
          can be rich and complex, or very simple. The same applies to its markup. Let's begin with
          the absolute minimum.</p>
        <p>A manuscript description should always tell you <list>
            <item>where the manuscript is to be found : <gi>msIdentifier</gi>
            </item>
            <item>what the manuscript contains : <gi>msContents</gi> or <gi>p</gi></item>
            <item>and probably something about its physical composition, size etc.
                (<gi>physDesc</gi> or <gi>p</gi>)</item>
          </list></p>
        <p>Of course it may contain much, much more, as we will see...</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Getting started</head>

        <p>In this exercise we will create a TEI document which contains a manuscript description,
          marked up with the TEI <gi>msDesc</gi> element. </p>
        <list>
          <item>Open oXygen, and create a new XML document using the template provided for a P5
            Manuscript Description <list>
              <item>Select New from the File menu (CTRL-N)</item>
              <item>Scroll down to Framework Templates in the New dialog</item>
              <item>Open TEI P5, and select Manuscript description </item>
            </list></item>
          <item>oXygen creates a template for you to fill which looks more or less like this
            <lb/>
            <graphic url="../Images/msDescSkel.png" width="60%"/></item>
          <item>First, fill in the TEI header as follows <list>
              <item>The <gi>title</gi> is something like <q>TEI Conformant description of a
                  manuscript</q></item>
              <item>The <gi>publicationStmt</gi> says something like <q>Unpublished
                exercise</q></item>
              <item>The <gi>sourceDesc</gi> for the moment says simply <q>No pre-existing
                source</q></item>
              <item>If you like, you could add a <gi>respStmt</gi> containing a <gi>resp</gi> such
                as <code>TEI Encoding</code> and a <gi>name</gi> containing your own name. Do you
                know where this element can go? How would you find out? </item>
            </list></item>
          <item>Next, fill in the <gi>msIdentifier</gi> as follows <list>
              <item>In the <gi>settlement</gi> element, give the name of the city (town, village,
                etc.) where your manuscript is currently stored (<q>Sofia</q>)</item>
              <item>In the <gi>repository</gi> element, give the name of the repository
                (institution, library, etc.) which holds it (<q>Национална Библиотека "Св. Св. Кирил
                  и Методий"</q>)</item>
              <item>In the <gi>idno</gi> element give the shelf mark, call number or similar for
                your manuscript (<q>1144</q>) </item>
            </list></item>
          <item>This is all that is needed for a valid manuscript description. But to make it
            useful, you may wish to add a little more information. You could supply this as a
              <gi>head</gi> element, for example containing the text <q>Short Apostle Lectionary in
              Russian, written in Cyrillic script by a single hand</q>. Or you could add a series of
              <gi>p</gi> or <gi>ab</gi> elements providing whatever information you choose. Or you
            could use some of the more specialised elements provided by the TEI, as follows.</item>
          <item>After the <gi>msIdentifier</gi>, add a <gi>msContents</gi> element to provide
            information about the <soCalled>intellectual content</soCalled> of the manuscript. In
            the simplest case, you might just want to summarise this, using a <gi>summary</gi>
            element. </item>
          <item>After the <gi>msContents</gi> element, add a <gi>physDesc</gi> element to describe
            the physical aspects of the manuscript. In the simplest case, you could provide this as
            one or more paragraphs (<gi>p</gi>) elements. </item>

        </list>

        <p>Your minimal <gi>msDesc</gi> should look something like this: <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <msDesc>
              <msIdentifier>
                <settlement>Sofia</settlement>
                <repository>National Library</repository>
                <idno>1144</idno>
              </msIdentifier>
              <head>Apostle Lectionary, in Russian, written in Cyrillic script by a single
                hand</head>
              <msContents>
                <summary>Apostle Lectionary in Russian</summary>
              </msContents>
              <physDesc>
                <p>Parchment, 39 folios, written in Cyrillic script by a single hand. Some damage to
                  outer leaves. </p>
              </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
          </egXML></p>
        <p>Since the <gi>head</gi> element now adds nothing to the rest of the description, you
          might like to remove it. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>A more ambitious description</head>
        <p>In this part of the exercise, we will first convert a pre-existing manuscript description
          from word processor format (Word or Libre Office) into TEI XML. We will then consider how
          each part of the description could be marked up in a TEI msDesc. </p>
        <list>
          <item>Browse to your <ident>Work</ident> folder and click on either the file
              <ident>LUL_Ms40.odt</ident> (if you have Libre Office) or <ident>LUL_Ms40.docx</ident>
            (if you have Microsoft Word) to open it. Take a quick look at its contents and close the
            word processor application again. </item>
          <item>Now, in oXygen, choose File - Open, navigate to this file, and open it again</item>
          <item>A new window labelled <ident>Archive Browser</ident> opens, showing the structure of
            the word processor file, which is actually a collection of several files. Find the file
            called <ident>content.xml</ident> (for an .odt file), or
              <ident>Word/document.xml</ident> (for a .docx file) and open it by double clicking on
            it</item>
          <item>As you can see, this is actually an XML file, although it uses a different non-TEI
            set of tags. We will use oXygen to convert it automatically into a basic TEI document. <list>

              <item><!--With the <ident>document.xml</ident> file open in your main editing window,-->
                Select <ident>Transformation -> Configure Transformation Scenario(s)</ident> from
                the <ident>Document</ident> menu. Or type <code>CTRL-SHIFT-C</code>. Or click the
                little spanner icon</item>
              <item>Check the little box next to DOCX TEI P5 (or ODT TEI P5) and press the
                  <ident>Apply Associated</ident> button.</item>
              <item>After a brief pause, a new window opens in which a basic TEI P5 version of the
                document appears. Click the Format and Indent button (CTRL-SHIFT-I) to see its
                structure, which should look familiar to you!</item>

            </list></item>
          <!--<item>You can if you wish revise the TEI Header to contain a title and other
              information, as you did before. The main part of this exercise is however to turn
              the body of this document into a properly structured TEI MS Description.</item>-->
        </list>
        <p>You could transform this document into a properly structured TEI MS Description in (at
          least) two ways. You could make a new document, using the template provided for a P5
          Manuscript Description in exactly the same way as before, and then gradually cut and paste
          material from one document into the other. Or you could change the tagging in the document
          you just created, deleting unnecessary additional material as you go. We don't mind which
          you choose, but we will describe the second. </p>
        <list>
          <item>If you adopt the second strategy, you will need to change the outermost <gi>div</gi>
            in the body of the document into an <gi>msDesc</gi> element. <list>
              <item>Highlight all the text inside the opening tag (<code>div type="div1"</code>)
                taking care <emph>not</emph> to include the pointy brackets. </item>
              <item>Type the new name you want (<code>msDesc</code>).</item>
              <item>Move the cursor outside the tag.</item>
              <item>If you scroll down to the end of the file, you will see that oXygen has
                helpfully inserted the closing tag. </item>
              <item>You will also see that the document is now invalid. Don't panic! You will fix
                this during the rest of the exercise. </item>
            </list></item>
          <item>Begin by creating a valid <gi>msIdentifier</gi> which shows that the manuscript with
            identifier <code>Medeltidshandskrift 40</code> is in the holdings of a repository called
              <code>Lund University Library</code>. If you like, you can additionally provide the
            country (Sweden), the town (Lund) and the institution (Lunds Universitet), each tagged
            with the appropriate TEI element. Don't forget that just typing a &lt; character
            anywhere in the document you are editing will pop up a list of the TEI tags available at
            this point: this will help you add the right tags within your <gi>msIdentifier</gi>
            element.</item>
          <item>This description includes two former identifiers (following the Latin word
              <q>olim</q>), which you should mark up using the <gi>altIdentifier</gi> element. We
            suggest that you regard <q>Bibliotheca recentior</q> as the name of a collection. And
            remember that you need to repeat the name of the host repository (<code>Lund University
              Library</code>) for each of these additional identifiers.</item>
          <item>This description also includes two summaries or abstracts, one very short, and one
            slightly longer. You can decide whether or not to keep them: if you do keep them, they
            can both by tagged using the <gi>head</gi> element. You could use the <att>type</att>
            attribute to distinguish them, if you like. </item>

        </list>
        <p>The start of your document should now look something like this: </p><p><graphic
            url="../Images/ms40_start.png" width="60%"/>
        </p>
        <p>The remainder of the description consists of a series of <gi>div</gi> elements, each
          containing a <gi>head</gi> to specify its function. Some (but not all) of these
            <gi>div</gi> elements can be translated immediately into a more specialised element, as
          follows: <list>
            <item>replace the <gi>div</gi> tag with its corresponding MsDesc element (see table
              below)</item>
            <item>delete the <gi>head</gi> element </item>
          </list>
          <table>
            <row role="label">
              <cell>heading</cell>
              <cell>element</cell>

            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Contents</cell>
              <cell><gi>msContents</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Physical description</cell>
              <cell><gi>physDesc</gi></cell>

            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Decoration</cell>
              <cell><gi>decoDesc</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Binding</cell>
              <cell><gi>bindingDesc</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Foliation</cell>
              <cell><gi>foliation</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Additions</cell>
              <cell><gi>additions</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Condition</cell>
              <cell><gi>condition</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>History</cell>
              <cell><gi>history</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Origin</cell>
              <cell><gi>origin</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Provenance</cell>
              <cell><gi>provenance</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
              <cell>Acquisition</cell>
              <cell><gi>acquisition</gi></cell>
            </row>
          </table></p>
        <p>Your document should now be valid at the start and the end, but not in the middle,
          because the sub-parts of the <gi>physDesc</gi> are not yet properly organised. We'll look
          at that in a moment, but first we'll tidy up the <gi>msContents</gi>.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Structuring the <gi>msContents</gi></head>
        <p>You can describe the intellectual content of a manuscript in many different ways. In the
          previous simple example we just supplied a <gi>summary</gi> element, which may be adequate
          in many cases. In a manuscript containing several different titles or items, it's more
          usual to supply a list of <gi>msItem</gi> elements for each one. Inside the
            <gi>msItem</gi> a number of more specialised elements are available to describe the item
          more exactly, such as a title, a rubric, an icipit etc. And we can also specify the part
          of a manuscript in which the item appears by using the <gi>locus</gi> element. </p>
        <list>
          <item>First, turn the first <gi>p</gi> element in the <gi>msContents</gi> element into an
              <gi>msItem</gi> element, in the same way as you transformed the outermost <gi>div</gi>
            tag into an <gi>msDesc</gi>. Highlight everything inside the first <gi>p</gi> tag (but
            not the pointy brackets), and type <code>msItem</code> to replace it.</item>
          <item>The figure 1 which follows is the number of this item within the manuscript. Add an
              <att>n</att> attribute to your <gi>msItem</gi> and give it this value. Then delete the
            whole of the <gi>hi</gi> element which contains the figure. </item>
          <item>Now look at the passage enclosed in parentheses ( and ). This contains a
              <gi>ref</gi> element whose <att>target</att> indicates an online version of this
            manuscript and which contains: <list>
              <item>an empty <gi>anchor</gi> element whose <att>xml:id</att> supplies an identifier
                for this item</item>
              <item>a <gi>hi</gi> element containing an indication of the folios in the manuscript
                concerned (<code>ff 6r-474v</code>)</item>
            </list> Proceed as follows: <list>
              <item>change the <gi>ref</gi> element into a <gi>locus</gi> element</item>
              <item>change its <att>target</att> attribute into a <att>facs</att> attribute</item>
              <item>move the <att>xml:id</att> attribute from the <gi>anchor</gi> to the
                  <gi>msItem</gi> you created earlier</item>
              <item>Delete the remaining parts of the <gi>hi</gi> elements and (if you like) the
                parentheses</item>
            </list>
          </item>
        </list>
        <p>The start of your msItem should now look like this:</p><p> <graphic
            url="../Images/msItemStart.png"/>.</p><p> We now need to tag the titles etc used to describe
          the work. <list>
            <item>Select the two words <q>Russkij Chronograf</q> and use CTRL-E to tag them as a
                <gi>title</gi></item>
            <item>Select the first passage within quotation marks labelled <q>rubric</q>, i.e. from
                <q>книга глаголемаꙗ</q> to <q>епископа гевалъскаго</q> and use CTRL-E to tag this as
              a <gi>rubric</gi>. Delete the <gi>hi</gi> element and the quotation marks.</item>
            <item>Do the same for the next quoted passage (from <q>зачало</q> to <q>землю</q>) but
              this time tag it as an <gi>incipit</gi></item>
            <item>Do the same for the next quoted passage (from <q>и многолѣтно</q> to <q>вѣки
                амин</q>) but this time tag it as an <gi>explicit</gi>
            </item>
            <item>And finally tag the stretch of text labelled as a colophon as a <gi>colophon</gi>
            </item>
            <item>Don't forget to remove the redundant <gi>hi</gi> and <gi>anchor</gi> elements left
              behind! Your <gi>msItem</gi> element should now be valid (i.e. no red underlining
              anywhere in it) </item>
          </list>
       </p><p>To check your work, open the Outline view (Window ->
       Show View -> Outline) to display the structure of your msDesc.  It should look
       something like this:</p><p>
       <graphic url="../Images/msItem.png"></graphic></p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Structuring the <gi>physDesc</gi></head>
        <p>The TEI schema distinguishes (and therefore tags) many distinct components within a
          physical description that is not just a sequence of paragraphs. Specifically, it
          distinguishes between information about the text bearing object itself, which is marked up
          using the <gi>objectDesc</gi> element, and information concerning aspects of the writing
          and decoration it carries. In some cases, the TEI schema also requires elements to be
          given in a specific order. To make our document valid, proceed as follows: <list>
            <item>Select the first two paragraphs (from "Support:" to "less details") and use CTRL-E
              to enclose these paragraphs with a <gi>support</gi> element. Delete the element
                <gi>hi</gi> with which it begins (both the tags and their content). </item>
            <item>Change the third <gi>p</gi> element (starting "Extent:") into an <gi>extent</gi>
              element. Delete the element <gi>hi</gi> with which it begins. </item>
            <item>Change the fourth <gi>p</gi> element (starting "Collation:") into a
                <gi>collation</gi> element. Delete the element <gi>hi</gi> with which it begins. </item>
            <item>Select the <gi>foliation</gi> element you created earlier and move it to follow
              the <gi>extent</gi> element</item>
            <item>Select the <gi>condition</gi> element you created earlier and move it to follow
              the <gi>foliation</gi> element</item>
            <item>Select all five elements, <gi>support</gi>, <gi>extent</gi>,
                <gi>collation</gi><gi>foliation</gi> and <gi>condition</gi>; use CTRL-E to wrap them
              in a <gi>supportDesc</gi> element</item>
            <item>Select the paragraph labelled <soCalled>Layout</soCalled>; use CTRL-E to enclose
              it first by a <gi>layoutDesc</gi> element, and then by a <gi>layout</gi> element.
              Delete the element <gi>hi</gi> with which it begins. </item>
            <item>Select the paragraph labelled <soCalled>Script</soCalled>; use CTRL-E to enclose
              it by a <gi>scriptDesc</gi> element. Delete the element <gi>hi</gi> with which it
              begins. </item>
            <item>Select the <gi>additions</gi> element you created earlier and move it to follow
              the <gi>decoDesc</gi> element</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Phew. If you have done all that correctly, your document is now valid and you have a
          jolly green square. Check the structure of your <gi>physDesc</gi> element in the
            <ident>Outline</ident> view: it should look like this: </p><p><graphic
            url="../Images/physDesc.png"/></p>
        <p>If you're still feeling strong, you might like to improve the markup of the
            <gi>support</gi> element as follows:<list>
            <item>Change the <gi>p</gi> element containing the word <q>Paper</q> into a
                <gi>material</gi> element</item>
            <item>Change the second <gi>p</gi> element into a <gi>watermark</gi> element</item>
            <item>Delete the text <code>Three different watermarks: 1)</code></item>
            <item>Split the <gi>watermark</gi> element into three by typing ALT-SHIFT-D before
                <code>2)</code> and <code>3)</code></item>
            <item> Delete the numbers 2) and 3)</item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>Our final version of this manuscript description is in the file
            <ident>Work/msDesc-corrected.xml</ident>. </p>
      </div>

     
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
